Welcome, students, to
the Pharmacology of the
Diuretic Agents. This
lecture is in two parts.
There is also a
supplemental video
that will talk about
the review questions at
the end of each
subclass of diuretics. I
won't go over the answers
in this main video.
Please contact me if
you'd like to talk about
pharmacology and our
learning objectives.
The kidneys maintain
plasma osmolality by
filtering blood and
precisely regulating
water and electrolyte
excretion. This you
have learned in your
physiology course.
Many diseases distort
the kidney's normal
ability to balance
sodium and water, and
this is where our
pharmacology comes in.
The goal of diuretic
therapy is to restore
and maintain uvolemia
by altering the
kidney's regulation
of sodium and water.
I cannot emphasize
strongly enough the
importance of understanding
renal physiology
in order to understand
pharmacology. It
is a necessity.
Preparation materials, practice
questions, are intended
to help you apply
what you have learned about
diuretic pharmacology.
The other materials
that I've listed
here are merely optional.
They're here if you'd
like to use them, If
anything works for you,
for gaining new
knowledge, it's up to you.
You certainly don't
have to use any
of them if they
don't work for you.
And resources.
And key points.
This is intended to
help you know what
it is you need to
know so that you
can focus on that.
And so we begin with the
principles of diuretic therapy.
This illustration
indicates the various
locations in which
the drugs act.
They are drugs that
act virtually at
every segment,
well not every, but
almost every segment
of the nephron.
I've indicated
with stars here the
drugs you should
know by name. Clearly
I haven't starred
every one of them.
the the drugs that you
need to know by name are
widely used some in some of
the classes I've indicated
in other drugs as well
and I will talk about
why you need to know them
what their drug specific
features are that separate
them within the class
and mechanisms, mechanisms,
mechanisms,
mechanisms of action,
mechanisms of adverse
effects, of drug interactions,
why we use them, the cautions
and contraindications,
and certainly the
pharmacokinetic
properties that actually
relate to patient care.
So, this is class
pharmacokinetics that
really represent the
entire class, well
nearly the entire
class, of diuretics.
I put on the right hand
side a column that says why
it matters. Hopefully,
this will help you to come
to appreciate the importance
of pharmacokinetics
in optimizing therapy for
our individual patient.
The various drugs
are oral, IV, IM.
Not all are in IV or IM.
And so it's agent-specific.
Absorption differs
among the agents. Some
have low bioavailability.
Others achieve excellent
plasma concentration.
So what is important
about this?
Predictability.
High bioavailability ensures
predictable delivery to
the kidney with a site
of action with consistent
diuretic effect. That's not
to say that the drugs that
have lesser bioavailability
can't be used. They can.
the high bioavailability
options may become important
in patients who are not
responding as expected
plasma protein binding
why do we care about that
especially with our diuretics
the highly protein bound
diuretics are not filtered
in other words they don't
filter and go through the
glomerulus but they enter
the nephron via secretion
into the proximal tubule
and these that we're
talking about now use the
organic anion transporters.
So how is this relevant?
Because organic anion
transport inhibitors
can reduce the
concentration of drug in
the nephron which can
reduce its efficacy.
And metabolism,
most of them are
not metabolized.
But metabolism, along
with absorption,
determines
bioavailability of drugs.
These drugs are excreted
in urine, which makes sense
because the sites of action
are in the nephron. And the
half-life varies according
to the individual drugs.
Diuretics decrease
extracellular fluid volume and
effective circulating volume,
which activates physiologic
compensatory responses.
We are going to be talking
about these compensatory
responses with every diuretic.
so please make sure you
understand these physiologic
responses so these i
will go over with you
increased sodium excretion
natriuresis which is what
we are aiming to achieve
with the diuretics and
an accompanying ion almost
always chloride will
decrease total body salt
content That's the point.
Increased water output
in the form of urine, and
that's called diuresis,
will decrease extracellular
fluid volume, interstitial
fluid and plasma volume.
now the duration of the
effect and the compensatory
response is going to depend
on number one the dose of the
diuretic the site of
action of the diuretic but
diuretics will cause volume
depletion that's the point and
volume depletion so reduced
plasma volume, is going to
trigger the sympathetic
nervous system activation and
the renin-angiotensin
-aldosterone system activation.
We will be talking a lot
about the RAS activation.
This is the slower,
dominant, sustained
effect. Now with RAS
activation comes the
aldosterone mediated
effects, the aldosterone
mediated sodium and
water retention.
So here we are trying
to reduce extracellular
fluid by increasing
the excretion of sodium
and the reduced
extracellular fluid volume
in turn activates RAS
and therefore aldosterone
will cause sodium
and water retention.
Another effect is decreased
effect of circulating
volume will cause the
baroreceptors to sense volume
depletion. That will cause
ADH release, antidiuretic
hormone, which is also
vasopressin. It's the same thing.
And ADH, then,
will cause expression,
or actually
translocation, of these
aquaporin channels,
AQP2 channels, to be
inserted in the
collect, oops, sorry,
to be inserted in
the collecting duct.
And then free water will be
reabsorbed. So water goes
back into increase the
effect of circulating volume.
Free water means it's
free of solutes. That's
why it's called free
water. No solutes.
Just water is being reabsorbed.
Well, clearly, with the
increase in sodium excretion
by blocking sodium
reabsorption, other
electrolyte handling is
going to be affected as well.
So potassium and sodium
and calcium and magnesium,
uric acid,
hyperuric acid secretion,
excretion can be inhibited.
We will talk about each
one of these mechanisms
with the specific drugs,
with the exception
of the potassium wasting
and sparing effects,
which I'll talk about
in the next two slides.
Just because adverse effects
happen doesn't mean we
can't use drugs. It means
we need to know what they
are, what we can expect, and
how we can mitigate them.
Monitoring.
So let's begin with the
mechanisms of the potassium
wasting effects. This is
the potassium loss that
occurs with the increase in
sodium excretion blocking
the sodium transport upstream
of the principal cells.
The principal cells are
located in the distal nephron.
They're called the
aldosterone-sensitive cells.
Upstream block of sodium
transport, so any place
above this distal nephron
location, which is in the
late DCT, late distal
convoluted tubule, the
connecting tubule, and the
collecting ducts, that's where
we're talking about with
these principal cells,
will increase the delivery
of sodium load to the
principal cells, obviously.
Blocked upstream, down
it comes. I've indicated
that by putting sodium
symbols into the space
that's called the lumen here.
sodium reabsorbs and then
happens by this channel
epithelial sodium channel it's
just just sodium is coming
in and we see the sodium
coming in the sodium going
out and this is our
sodium pump here. So the
potassium comes in and now
because of this change with the
increase in intracellular
potassium favors movement
of potassium into the lumen
through this ROMK channel,
which is a leak channel,
and potassium goes out.
So that's the basic
potassium losing effect.
Well, no, not exactly.
Let's back up.
By sodium going in,
that will increase the
lumen-negative electrical
gradient, and we
see our potassium is
coming in here and it is
this increase in lumen
negative electrical
gradient that favors
potassium to move out.
Block sodium upstream,
sodium load comes downstream,
sodium goes that's
absorbed through epithelial
sodium channel that
causes increased
potassium amount, potassium
secretion increases.
Now, the second mechanism is
related to volume depletion
by the diuretic. The
volume depletion causes
activation of the renin
-angiotensin-aldosterone system, and
I put aldosterone here,
and aldosterone now will
increase expression of the
epithelial sodium channel,
increase activity of the
sodium potassium ATPase, and
increase the activity of the
ROMK, and that will further
increase the potassium
secretion and potassium loss,
so potassium wasting effect.
And decreasing potassium,
increasing potassium loss,
will decrease plasma potassium
and that can lead
to hypokalemia.
Potassium wasting effect.
Now let's look at the
potassium sparing effect. This
occurs with diuretics
that act at the level of
the principal cells. They
act either by blocking the
epithelial sodium channel
or by blocking the
mineralocorticoid receptor,
which would be, let me put
this here, mineralocorticoid
receptor gets blocked.
So
let's see what happens.
Block epithelial sodium
channel. Now, you
may recall that it was
sodium going in that
will create this lumen
-negative potential.
Well, blocking this
will therefore diminish,
even abolish that lumen
-negative potential.
And now potassium can no longer
be drawn in down its gradient.
Sodium's not going in.
Everything slows down
on the inside. lumen
negative potential
diminishes, and potassium
doesn't come in.
Potassium doesn't go
out, less potassium is
coming in, stays pretty
much in the bloodstream.
Potassium sparing effect.
Mineralocorticoid
receptor antagonists
decrease aldosterone
activity by inhibiting
the mineralocorticoid
receptor and therefore
they will have very
much the same effect.
They decrease sodium
reabsorption. Sodium in the lumen
causes a decrease in the
lumen negative potential.
Potassium secretion is
blunted, potassium sparing
effect. Now, the
magnitude of the potassium
sparing effect with the
mineralocorticoid receptor
antagonist is obviously
going to be related
to how much aldosterone
is around beforehand.
What are we using
them for? Well, edema.
Any type of of condition
where there is edema in
which that edema fluid needs
to be removed. And that's
generally the loop diuretics.
And you'll see why.
That is the second group of
diuretics I'll talk about.
Loop diuretics are
powerful. They mobilize that
extracellular fluid into the
plasma and from the plasma
into the kidneys for
excretion in order to manage
the volume overload, to
reduce that volume overload.
In terms of conditions
that are not related
to edema, hypertension
is at the top of
the list, and this is
thiazide diuretics that
are used for this.
They are, in In fact,
a guideline
recommended first line,
along with a couple
of other classes.
And they decrease peripheral
vascular resistance,
and that's how they
manage hypertension.
And they do produce
a sustained effect.
Thiazides decrease calcium
excretion. So they may be
used in patients with
hypercalciuria, too much calcium
in the urine, to prevent
kidney stone recurrence.
Nephrogenic diabetes
insipidus. I'll
go into more detail
on that later.
Lithium toxicity. I'll
talk more about that.
Potassium sparing. We
already talked about that.
Hyperaldosteronism.
In other words, any type
of condition that causes
excessive aldosterone
release, then it makes sense
that a mineralocorticoid
receptor antagonist would
be used. it blocks the
effect of the aldosterone.
Mountain sickness and
glaucoma with the carbonic
anhydrase inhibitors I'll
talk about when we get there.
And then we'll
talk about osmotic
diuretics last. So
that's a quick overview.
I do want to talk about
prostaglandins and NSAIDs.
Cyclooxygenase 1 and
2 and prostaglandin
receptors are expressed
in vascular, glomerular,
and tubular compartments
of the kidney.
The ***-1, which is
constitutive, is indicated
on this figure as
this sort of light
green color. I'm not
sure you all can see it.
And ***-2 is indicated
in the blue color.
So you can see that
the cyclooxygenase and
prostaglandins are
extremely important in the
functioning of the
kidney across the kidney.
PGE2 and prostacyclin, PGI2,
are the primary bioactive
prostaglandins that are
generated within the
kidney, especially PGE2. It
has many, many functions.
PGE2 and PGI2 counteract
vasoconstriction. I'm
sure you remember this
from the NSAIDs lecture.
And by maintaining a dilation
of the afferent arteriole,
they will maintain renal
blood flow and glomerular
filtration pressure, and
consequently GFR, glomerular
filtration rate. And
this supports natrioresis
and promotes renin release,
depending on the context.
During states of stress,
PGE2 and PGI2, prostacycline,
are critical to preserving
renal blood flow.
So that brings me to
the topic of NSAIDs.
NSAIDs substantially reduce
the efficacy of diuretics.
They reduce the synthesis
of prostaglandins
throughout the nephron, as
you can see from the figure.
They cause vasoconstriction
of the afferent
arteriole, decrease
renal perfusion,
reduce GFR, cause sodium
and water retention.
Sodium and water
retention can cause
edema, worsen heart
failure, worsen
blood pressure. in
vulnerable patients.
These are review questions
that I won't go over now.
It will be in the
supplemental video.
The answers are at the
end. I invite you to just
answer these questions
for yourself right
now, the best you can,
just to make sure that you
refresh the information
we just went through.
If you want to pause
the video, these are the
answers, or they're
at the end, as I said.
And more questions with
a very brief case vignette.
So, let's actually begin
the diuretic agents.
We will talk about this
group within this box.
The drugs that modify
water excretion,
I'm not going to
mention in this lecture.
Carbonic anhydrase inhibitors
act in the proximal
tubule. And they
obviously inhibit carbonic
anhydrase. The drug that
I'd like you to remember by
name is acetazolamide.
They are potent and
reversible inhibitors of both
membrane-bound and cytosolic
carbonic anhydrase in
the proximal tubule.
And carbonic anhydrase
is also important in the
distal tubule, so these
drugs will block that too.
this figure here shows carbonic
anhydrase activity in
the proximal tubule
so the physiology is
here i'm not going
to go through the
physiology we'll just talk
about what's happening
with the drugs.
This is the NHE3, that's the
sodium, a hydrogen
ion antiporter.
Sodium goes in,
hydrogen goes out.
Hydrogen will combine
with the filtered
bicarbonate, It's
coming through
the glomerulus from
the bloodstream.
That will form
carbonic anhydrase,
which will form water and CO2.
And our drugs are
blocking this step.
But further down, CO2 goes
in intracellularly to form
carbonic anhydrase again.
And our drugs block here.
So, by blocking carbonic
anhydrase, that's going to
prevent the reabsorption
of bicarbonate and sodium.
So, bicarbonate and sodium
will be inhibited and
go out through the lumen
along with, of course,
water.
So this is going to
increase the flow, sodium
load, the water flow
through the lumen.
Now, let's talk about
efficacy for a second.
Talk about that yet.
So if we know that about
a third of sodium is
reabsorbed, a third of
filtered sodium that's a lot of
sodium 66 percent it's
reabsorbed here and we're
blocking all of this that's
a big sodium load going out
and with it a commensurate
amount of water but as
we're going to see carbonic
anhydrase inhibitors really
are quite weak diuretics
and why is that because
as the sodium and water
flow through from the
proximal tubular tubule on
down through the whole rest
of the nephron and up
through the thick ascending
limb in the distal convoluted
tubule and out through
the collecting tubules,
there's opportunity to be
reabsorbed along the way.
So a large amount of the
sodium load will be reabsorbed
and with it the water.
So let's talk about
now what can happen
when we inhibit
carbonic anhydrase.
We get something called a mild,
it's not strong,
but it does occur,
hyperchloremic metabolic
acidosis, a metabolic acidosis,
and also self-limited diuretic
effects. So how do
these things happen?
Carbonic anhydrase
inhibition leads to this
massive bicarbonate
loss. So I said the
sodium gets reabsorbed,
but the bicarbonate
keeps going through,
and that's lost in the
urine. A large amount
of bicarbonate is lost.
Continued bicarbonate loss
reduces plasma bicarbonate.
So, I mean, the drug is
on board, continues to
block carbonic anhydrase.
Plasma bicarbonate continues
to be filtered through
the glomerulus, continues
to be excreted. chloride
is reabsorbed to maintain
electroneutrality so that's
down here in the intercalated
cell hydrogen normally
will be secreted by
carbon it normally will be
exported into the bloodstream
and chloride would be
brought in for neutral for
electron neutrality two
negative anion, two anions.
Well,
everything gets blocked.
So as a result, we get this
massive hyperchloramic,
so the chloride actually
goes back in, or stays in.
Bicarbonate is not going out.
Hydrogen is not being
secreted, and that
can lead to this
metabolic acidosis.
Now, what about the self
-limited diuretic effect? And
we're talking about just
a few days of continuous
therapy, and a given dose will
no longer be as effective.
So we know there's a lower
amount of filtered bicarbonate.
And as a result, there
is a lower amount
of sodium that's
being blocked. Sodium
reabsorbs in this
block. So more sodium is
being reabsorbed in
the proximal tubule.
So there's less natriuresis,
less diuresis. So
that's a reduced efficacy
right there. Besides the
fact that such a small
amount of sodium actually
gets excreted with carbonic
anhydrase inhibition.
And there is a decrease
in ECF volume. plus,
along with the metabolic
acidosis, we get
activation of the renin
-angiotensin-aldosterone
system. So, aldosterone
is available. And we also
get vasopressin ADH
secretion is stimulated.
And that whole thing is going
to increase the expression
of the epithelial sodium
channel for more sodium
reabsorption as well as
increase the insertion of
aquaporin channels and therefore
more water reabsorption.
So reduced diuretic
efficacy. On top of it, the
carbonic anhydrase
inhibitors do cause potassium
wasting. It's a mild effect.
It's commensurate with the
amount of sodium that's
being excreted or i should
say being reabsorbed by the
epithelial sodium channel
so potassium wasting
effect that's mild mild
metabolic acidosis but
nonetheless acidosis
this is just a review
of the different effects
of carbonic anhydrase
on electrolyte patterns
urinary electrolytes
plus a recap of the
effects of the carbonic
anhydrase inhibitors.
I'm not going to go
through this slide
I invite you to view
it at your leisure.
Let's talk about what
they're for. So acute
mountain sickness or acute
high altitude sickness.
Acetazolamide is commonly
used for prevention
and treatment so how
is this working? Well
first of all we have
to think about what's
going on with this
high altitude effects.
A person quickly goes
to a high altitude where
there is less oxygen,
less oxygen pressure in
the atmosphere, so people
start to hyperventilate,
and that can cause
hyperventilation-induced
alkalosis, which is going
to inhibit the peripheral
chemoreceptors and the
respiratory center.
So by inducing a mild
metabolic acidosis with the
acetazolamide, that
will override, that will
counteract, either way you
want to say it, the inhibitory
effect on the respiratory
center and the
chemoreceptors, and that
will increase the minute
ventilation, causing an
increase in CO2 exhalation, but
the whole point of it
is to obtain sustained
hyperventilation, which will
improve oxygenation, and
therefore these high
-altitude symptoms diminish.
in glaucoma it's a different
effect because the carbonic
anhydrase will be
reducing the formation of
bicarbonate which is used
in the production of aqueous
humor so reduced aqueous
humor secretion is going to
reduce intraocular pressure
and that will reduce the
pressure on the optic
nerve. In terms of metabolic
alkalosis, well, induction of
metabolic acidosis would be
an adjunctive approach.
It's especially useful for
loop diuretic-induced
hypokalemic metabolic alkalosis.
It gets basically to the cause.
It's not used in
edema because they're
low efficacy. They
have such a low
amount of natriuresis
and diuresis.
The carbonic anhydrase
inhibitors remain highly
effective in the
treatment of mountain
sickness and also glaucoma.
In other words, the
effect is not self-limited.
And this is because
the metabolic acidosis
is not self-limited.
And in glaucoma treatment,
it's not self-limited
because it's actually
not relying on filtered
bicarbonate. It's
preventing the production of
bicarbonate in the ciliary
epithelium. adverse
effects. Well, metabolic
acidosis, which
we talked about, it
is a side effect, and
it's a side effect that's
used to therapeutic
advantage in acute
mountain sickness.
Potassium wasting,
certainly it's mild though.
All this bicarbonate being
secreted in being excreted
in the urine is going to
cause an alkaline urine,
and that favors the precipitation
of calcium phosphate
crystals, so kidney stones,
and it does cross the
blood-brain barrier and
there will be common CNS side
effects. They're not really
basically harmful, but
they can be very annoying
and concerning to patients.
Paresthesia, somnolence,
dizziness,
ataxia, headache, and so on.
Contraindications. Well,
clearly we're not going to
use it in a patient with
acidosis, or severe renal
disease, or cirrhosis from
severe hepatic disease.
In hepatic disease, the
ammonia can accumulate
because it's not being
metabolized properly.
And CA inhibitors can
contribute to hyperammonemia,
which I'm not going through
that whole mechanism.
hypersensitivity to the
drug or any component
of the formulation
and that's always
true whether I put
it on the list or not
here are the key points
of what we talked about
with the carbonic anhydrase
inhibitors I invite
you to see if you can
remember anything about it
and here are the
answers if you want to
pause your computer
or look at the end
And a couple of more.
On to the loop diuretics.
This will be the last
subclass that we talk
about in this part one.
Loop diuretics are very,
very important drugs.
They inhibit the
NKCC2 in the thick
ascending limb of
the loop of Henle.
The ones I put STARS
on are furosemide,
torsemide, and ethacrinic acid.
Bumetanide is another
one in the group.
It's long-acting. That's really
basically its difference
from furosemide.
Ethacrinic acid is here
for a reason I'll talk
about on the next slide. I
want to draw your attention
to this update. Some of
you may be aware that
loop diuretics, thiazide
diuretics, carbonic
anhydrase diuretics have
something called a sulfonamide
moiety on their structures.
And because of that,
because of the sulfonamide
moiety, which you may
recognize as being like
sulfonamide antibiotics,
it has traditionally
been recommended
not to give these
drugs to people who
have a severe sulfonamide
allergy. Well,
studies go on, research
continues, and it's been found
that the risk of cross
-reactivity in persons with
a history of sulfonamide
allergy is clinically
insignificant. And this is most
likely a structure-activity
relationship because diuretics
lack something called
this N4-aromatic amine
that is implicated in the
sulfonamide allergic reactions,
immunogenic reactions.
And because the diuretics
don't have it, they're not
really associated with this
immune-mediated reaction.
so I bring it up because
you could hear about this
on a board exam you can
see it on a board exam you
could see it in your
preparation questions for the
boards they will be suggesting
to use ethacrinic acid
which does not have the
sulfonamide moiety so I want
you to be able to differentiate
between what you might
see on an exam and what
you might find when you
are actually in your clinical
rotations and practice.
These loop diuretics,
I put an arrow here
pointing to the
thick ascending limb.
The takeaways regarding
the loop diuretics
are really what to
use for refractory
edema. This is how you
can tell them apart.
And I put some circles
down here at the,
what am I saying, the
duration of action.
Furosemide, probably, no
definitely the most widely
used of the loop diuretics.
Comes in a variety of
different ways to administer
it. It has moderate
absorption, and I'll come
back to this in a second.
They are very highly
plasma protein bound, so
they go through the kidney
via the organic anti-ion
transporters, which
this is related. This is
class effect. You need to
know the class effects.
And the duration of
diuresis is not really long.
Now, let's talk
about torsemide. This
is the difference
from the furosemide.
It's got great bioavailability.
So, sometimes the
absorption really matters.
So, patients with heart
failure, for example, may
not absorb furosemide
as well as patients who
otherwise have great absorption
through the gut mucosa.
because heart failure
patients can have GI edema
and the drugs just are
not absorbed as well. So
what do we do then? Well,
we can move to a drug
that's got great bioavailability
and that is torsemide.
So in patients with
refractory edema, edema
that's not responding to
furosemide at high doses,
then it makes sense
to switch over to the
torsemide, which does have
predictable absorption.
even in patients
with gut edema.
And it also has a
longer half-life and
longer duration of
action than furosemide.
Now, ethacrinic acid. These
are the takeaways. This
is what I want you to
remember from ethacrinic acid.
It lacks the sulfonamide
moiety, and therefore
it was recommended
for decades to be used
in patients with the
sulfonamide allergy.
It is not more effective than
the other loop diuretics.
It does not have any
pharmacokinetic advantages.
The ototoxicity risk
is higher than with the
other loop diuretics.
It is very expensive.
And because it's
not very widely
used, its availability
may be limited.
Takeaways with ethacrinic
acid. Takeaways with
torsemide, which is great
bioavailability, refractory
edema, and longer duration
of action. and furosemide,
which is so widely used
and comes in a variety of
different ways to administer
it. IB is very frequent.
And it's not too well absorbed
in patients with gut edema.
And otherwise, it's the same
class pharmacokinetic effects.
How do they work?
They're called potent
diuretics because
they will block
up to 25% of the
sodium load, which
is a lot of sodium.
And therefore, they will
cause a large amount of
water to be excreted. Rapid
natriuresis and diuresis.
Potent. So that's where
the efficacy comes
from. its effect on
natrioresis and diuresis.
Now, what happens when
we block the NKCC2?
Well, we're going
to eliminate this
transepithelial potential here.
You see it's indicated there.
Magnesium and calcium
normally pass through
between the epithelial
cells and are
reabsorbed that way.
Well, this gets lost.
So, magnesium and calcium
are excreted as well.
So, all of these are
excreted. Sodium, potassium,
potassium here also,
magnesium,
calcium, and chloride.
And here's our physiology,
if you want to look at that.
okay the compensatory
responses now so large
amount of natrioresis diuresis
that's going to affect
the renal hemodynamics
now an interesting
thing about loop diuretics
is that they actually
stimulate, directly
stimulate, the intrarenal PGE2
and PGI2 secretion. The
others don't do that.
And that's going to
increase renal blood
flow, so vasodilation
of the afarin arterial.
And the GFR is going to
briefly increase, but then
it'll be preserved by other
compensatory mechanisms.
Then, all of this
natriuresis, diuresis,
there will be significant
volume contraction,
RAS activation, and RAS now,
angiotensin 2,
is going to cause
constriction of the
efferent arteriole.
The whole system
is going to cause
increased sodium and
water reabsorption.
There's going to
be a mild decline
in renal blood flow and in GFR.
So impaired urine
concentration and
dilution. This is an
important concept.
So think about this.
We're blocking NKCC2 there
in the thick ascending
limb of the loop of Henley.
The thick ascending
limb and the distal
convoluted tubule are
impermeable to water.
So there's water
already in the nephron.
We're blocking NKCC2.
We're increasing the
amount of solutes in
that ultrafiltrate.
So now it has a much greater
concentration of
solutes in there.
So this is going to
impair dilution of the
urine because it's got
so much solutes in there.
At the same time,
we're blocking NKCC2.
Sodium is not going into
the medulla, so it's not
increasing the gradient, the
medullary gradient. So that's
called collapse of the
medullary gradient. And why
do we need the medullary
gradient in the first place?
It's so from the collecting
duct side, water will
be reabsorbed from the
collecting duct, if
there are aquaporin 2
channels in place, and it
will flow passively into
this concentrated medulla
down the gradient, down
the osmotic gradient.
And that's very important
for absorption of free water.
And free water
absorption is necessary
in order to
concentrate the urine.
So what happens is,
by blocking NKCC2,
the kidneys are not able
to concentrate urine,
and the kidneys are not
able to dilute urine.
And now diuretic resistance.
I'll talk more about
that on the next slide.
But diuretic resistance
definition is edema, refractory
to typically effective
doses of loop diuretic. And
it can occur because of
compensatory tubular adaptations,
renal hemodynamics, and
pharmacokinetic mechanisms
that together reduce
sodium and water excretion.
And I want to remind
you about NSAIDs.
blocking prostaglandin
synthesis is going
to reduce the effect
of loop diuretics.
Okay,
physiologies on top,
concentration and
dilute urine, urine
dilution, I should say.
So this is basically
what I just
explained on the
previous slide about
concentrating and
diluting the urine.
A diuretic resistance,
edema refractory to
typically effective
doses, and it's also
known as a diuretic
breaking phenomenon.
It can happen with
thiazide diuretics,
but is by far the most
prominent with loop
diuretics, most
clinically significant.
The primary mechanism with
chronic use we're talking
about is a distal nephrine
adaptation. hypertension,
hypertrophy of the
distal segments. So these
are the segments below
the thick ascending limb.
And that's going to
cause upregulation
of the sodium chloride channel,
epithelial sodium channel, and
the sodium potassium ATPases.
And as a result, there will be
increased
reabsorption capacity.
So that's primary
mechanism is this
hypertrophy that
causes increased sodium
reabsorption. Now this
whole, this process is
amplified by the volume
depletion that comes along with
loop diuresis and natriuresis
by loop diuretics.
So
So, these actions with
aldosterone and ADH are
going to increase sodium
and water reabsorption.
This macula densa suppression,
I haven't gone over
macula densa. It isn't usually
clinically significant.
It's an interesting mechanism,
but it's not clinically
significant, usually. but
suppressing macula densa by
blocking NKCC2 is going
to stimulate renin release
which supports this RAS activity
and contributing factors
are decreased absorption
from gut edema I mentioned
that before and that's
going to reduce the delivery
of drug to the site of action
impaired proximal tumular
secretion, OAT inhibition,
higher sodium intake, so
the balance is off, you've
got more sodium coming in,
and drug interactions,
NSAIDs, especially,
and probenicid OAT
inhibitors. Those three
mechanisms you should be
familiar with in relation
to refractory edema.
So this is just a scheme
pointing out the different
locations of the actions that
cause diuretic resistance
and the conditions that
can cause refractory edema.
so what do we do normally
we don't talk about
management per se and what
i'm doing really here is
applying your pharmacology
knowledge so the first thing
to do is make sure there's
no excessive salt intake
and drug interactions
are rolled out those are
the easy things right off
the top check the dose of
the loop diuretic check
whether the patient's
adherent to the loop diuretic
maybe you need to increase
the loop diuretic maybe
you need to split it up
in two to three divided
doses so it's on board for
a longer period of time
because when it wears off
then we're going to get the
sodium and water reabsorption
uh maybe a switch to
torsemide would be appropriate
remember torsemide is oral
now if that's inadequate
if all of that is
inadequate, canada thiazide
diuretic, and you get the
sequential nephron blockade.
So you see how to look
at this in terms of
application of these
diuretic principles.
And this is just a
refresher on the loop
diuretics, and I put
it into comparison
with the carbonic
anhydrase inhibitors.
Okay, what do we use
it for? Well, edema.
Edema, edema, edema
from any cause.
All of this is related
to edema. I want to draw
your attention here to
chronic kidney disease.
This higher doses may be needed
because of this
shift to the right.
there are it's because
of diuretic resistance
hypertension thiazides
really are first first line
well we know loop diuretics
could decrease blood pressure
right so why aren't they
first line well because
of this risk of volume and
electrolyte depletion that's
much greater than we see
with the thiazides also
the their action is short
-lived, whereas the thiazides,
the way they work, can
produce a sustained blood
pressure lowering effect.
So they're more, they're
really better for hypertension
than the loop diuretics.
And forced diuresis
for chemotherapy, this
is sort of falling
out. It's still around,
but because this forced
diuresis is associated
with some pretty
severe adverse effects.
So it must be done
very carefully by
people who are
experienced with doing it.
And adverse effects
related to electrolyte
balance, water and electrolyte
balance. It makes
all kinds of sense.
So we'll talk about the
mechanism of hypokalemic
metabolic alkalosis
now. So we know they
cause potassium wasting.
And because they
are strong natriuretics,
they can cause
significant potassium
wasting with hypokalemia.
They also will cause
loss of hydrogen
secretion. That's just
part of the process.
And aldosterone is
involved in that. Volume
contraction with RAS
activation. We talked about
that a number of times.
and that's going to
promote proximal tubule
bicarbonate reabsorption.
That's a compensatory
response. Chloride
loss, because it's being
lost with the sodium,
along with bicarbonate
release exportation into
the bloodstream from
the intercalated cells.
so that everything together
can produce metabolic
alkalosis and because of
the potassium loss it's
hypokalemic metabolic
alkalosis and other toxicities
ototoxicity is well known
as loop diuretics because
it blocks the nkcc one type
within the ear and that's
going to disrupt the
potassium balance in there.
So that will disrupt
balance and hearing.
Hyperuricemia, because it
interferes with
uric acid excretion.
Hypersensitivity
reactions, of course,
we always have to
think about that.
But they are rare.
Pregnancy, this is related
to the risk of decreasing
placental perfusion, which
it certainly will do.
And so they should not be
used unless the benefit
outweighs, the benefit
to the mother outweighs
the risk to the fetus and
with careful monitoring
by people who are
experienced in its use.
Oh, lots of drug interactions.
Well, thiazide, That's
a good interaction.
Synergy will really
increase the diuresis.
Antihypertensive agents
with low blood pressure.
They both lower blood pressure.
ACE inhibitors and ARBs. This
is the nephrotoxicity risk.
The ACE inhibitors and
ARBs will interfere with
a compensatory mechanism
that protects the GFR.
Lithium absorption.
Lithium and sodium are taken
up by the same mechanism,
and we are blocking that
with the loop diuretics.
It so happens that loop
diuretics have a smaller
effect on lithium reabsorption
than thiazides do,
which we'll talk about when
we get to the thiazides.
Digitalis glycosides.
Well, hypokalemia can
increase digitalis
toxicity because of the
digitalis mechanism, which
is transported, which
blocks, I should say,
a potassium channel.
And I'll let you
learn about that when
you get to the
heart failure drugs.
And hypokalemia
can, with digitalis
toxicity, can
cause arrhythmias.
Quinidine and other
QT interval prolonging
drugs because of the
drug-induced hypokalemia.
So QT interval prolonging
plus hypokalemia increase
the risk of thoracetoplamine,
ventricular arrhythmia.
uh anti-diabetic drugs
because loop diuretics can
impair glucose control
not to the same extent
as the thiazides but
still somewhat probenicid
well blocking organic
anion transporters NSAIDs
we've talked about quite
a bit glucocorticoids
because they too can increase
the risk of hypokalemia,
and they promote sodium
and potassium retention,
sorry, sodium retention
and potassium loss,
amphotericin B because
of the increased
risk of hypokalemia
plus renal injury,
aminoglycosides because
of the nephrotoxicity
and ototoxicity of
both aminoglycosides
and loops, And the same
thing with cisplatin.
And cisplatin uses
forced diuresis
to help mitigate
the nephrotoxicity.
So thinking about
cisplatin nephrotoxicity,
ototoxicity, therosemide
nephrotoxicity,
ototoxicity, that can
be an additive effect.
And here are the
review questions
to check your knowledge.
here are the answers
if you want to look at
them now or wait till
later and cover some more
review questions and a
little tiny case vignette
and that brings us to
the end of this video
and this is just a stretched
out nephron showing
all of the different
functions and electrolyte
movement in the various
sections, segments of
the nephron. And I put
here just a review of the
topics and the answers to
the questions, which I'm
not going through, as I've
said a bunch of times now.
We'll talk about that
another time. And diabetic
therapy can dramatically
improve true quality of life.
And I relate to
this couple dancing.
That concludes part one.